Well, all right. Welcome to unit 6. And
you didn't think we weren't going to
keep talking about westward expansion in
this unit, did you? Don't be crazy. No,
that development continued right on into
this new time period. So, I'm going to
keep flapping my mouth hole about it.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay. So,
let's start by talking about the causes
of westward migration and our brand
spanking new time period for this unit,
namely 1865 to 1898. And it's going to
be helpful for you to remember that
westward migration has connections
throughout all the prior units that
we've covered in this fair course. Most
relevant here is the market revolution
that you learned in unit 4 and then
let's be honest slipped right out of
your brain through your ear hole and
settled upon that pile of forgotten
detritus that resides on your shoulder.
So let me remind you that the market
revolution was the big movement that
knit together the various regions of the
United States into an interdependent
economic hole. And a big part of that
was Americans migrating westward on
account of the lure of cheaper land. And
furthermore, when all that westward
movement and more productive
agricultural output contributed to the
growth of the US economy, that had a way
of reinforcing the idea of manifest
destiny. So, all that to say, the causes
of westward migration in this unit are
in many ways just a continuation of the
same causes that we've considered
before. And there are three big causes
for migration in this period that you're
going to need to cram into those
delicate brain folds of yours. So, first
we have government land grants, which
came through the Homestead Acts of 1862.
So, as I mentioned in the last unit,
this set of policies granted 160 acre
plots to any American who committed to
migrating west and improving the land on
which they lived for 5 years. And when I
say granted, I mean the land was
straight up free, like on the house. So,
as you might imagine, a metric buttload
of Americans decided to take up the
government on this offer and made plans
to relocate their hind parts west of the
Mississippi River. However, it turned
out that traveling to the Great Plains
via overland trails was still difficult
work. So, that leads us to the second
cause of westward expansion. So in order
to further encourage westward migration
and settlement, Congress facilitated the
construction of several transcontinental
railroads. Now the Republicans in
Congress sort of viewed themselves as
the heirs of Henry Clay's American
system, which if you'll recall from unit
4, majored in government sponsored
infrastructure projects like bridges and
roads, except here they turned their
sights on connecting the whole of the US
via railroad. To that end, Congress
appropriated millions of acres of land
in the western territories to large
railroad companies. And those companies
used that land to construct their rail
lines and then sold the excess acreage
in order to fund the construction. And
so in 1863, work on the first
transcontinental railroad began, the
labor for which was largely provided by
Chinese and Irish immigrants. So the
Central Pacific Company started work in
Sacramento, California, while the Union
Pacific Company started work in Council
Bluffs, Iowa. And in 1869, the two crews
met in Promontory Point, Utah, and
completed the rail line by driving a
golden spike into the joint where they
both met. So, the completion of this
railroad facilitated an enormous upsurge
in westward migration since rail travel
was way faster than overland travel and
much cheaper. And even more than that,
railroads also facilitated the expansion
of markets and the growth of new trading
hubs like Chicago and other cities along
major routes. And then by the end of the
19th century, four additional
transcontinental railroads had been
completed. And that meant that Americans
were settling the west quick, fast, and
in a hurry. Okay. And then the third
cause of westward migration was the
expansion of communication technology,
most notably the telegraph. So, Congress
made sure that wherever railroads were
constructed, telegraph wires followed
right along. This meant that even as
Americans were becoming more
geographically separated, they could
still communicate across great distances
instantaneously, which also had the
effect of expanding commercial markets.
And so, with all three of those
developments working handinhand,
Americans flooded into the American
West. And now let's consider how it
actually went when they got there. But
before I do, let me just mention that
you might want to have a look at my A
Push Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
It's got exclusive unit review videos
that are not here on YouTube, practice
questions, practice exams, and answer
keys for every dang bit of it. It's
definitely the fastest way to study. So,
if that's the kind of thing you're into,
the link is in the description. Okay, so
we've established that big daddy
government is doing out free land with
all the eagerness of those guys handing
out flyers on city sidewalks. But unlike
those guys on the corner, Americans were
real excited to take these flyers and
get moving. And they were excited even
though some educated geological people
were all like, "Actually, that great
plains land might be a little hard to
farm." And as it turned out, when many
migrants settled on their 160 acre
plots, they soon found that the
geological egghehead was kind of right.
It was way harder to make a life on the
Great Plains than they had expected. In
fact, it soon became clear that the only
real way to succeed in farming out there
was to cultivate way more than 160
acres. And so by the end of the 19th
century, about 2/3 of the independent
farmers who had settled in the Great
Plains had gone bankrupt. And if you
listen very carefully, you can hear the
faint sounds of a mournful tear running
down Thomas Jefferson's face. Like
remember, this was always his vision, an
agrarian American West filled with
independent farmers. But unfortunately
for Mr. Jefferson, not so much. Now, the
homesteaders that didn't fold were able
to make it because they employed two
strategies. First, they used a technique
called dry farming, which required a
deep plowing of the earth in order to
get to the moist soil below the dry
dust. However, this technique required
new technology like steel plows and
steam powered tractors to pull them. And
as it turned out, these tools were uh
real expensive and therefore out of
reach for most ordinary farmers. It
would kind of be like if you had to take
the SAT with a golden pencil and the
machine could only read answers that
were filled in with gold. Like, it
wouldn't matter how much you actually
know if you don't have that golden
pencil, which most students can't
afford, then it doesn't matter because
you about to fail that test real hard.
Anyway, the second strategy successful
farmers used was the planting of a
European style hard kernel wheat seed
that was resistant to extreme weather.
Okay, so what's going to happen to all
those farmers who couldn't afford the
golden pencil and had to fold? Well,
that leads right into the next major
development during this period, namely
the commercialization of agriculture and
ranching. What I mean is since the
technology to make farming work on the
Great Plains was too expensive for most
common farmers, many of them folded on
their farms and sold them to big
agricultural corporations. See, these
corporations could afford the technology
required to plant at scale in the West.
And by consolidating millions of acres
of land acquired from failing
homesteaders, they had the space
required to run successful agricultural
operations on a scale that would be
impossible for individual farmers. And
don't forget, it was the growing
railroad infrastructure that made
possible this consolidation and
commercialization of agriculture. The
big effect of which was to integrate
western farms with eastern markets. And
it wasn't just agriculture that
experienced such a development. It was
cattle ranchers as well. You see, the
fabled western cattle drives carried out
by cowboys in the past became nearly
impossible due to overg grazing in the
plains and the multiplication of
barbedwire fences that homesteaders
erected around their farms. You see, the
fences protected their farms, but they
also drastically reduced the acorage
available for cattle to graze during
their long drives to market. And so, by
the mid 1880s, a few wealthy commercial
ranchers owned something like 40 million
acres of land on which they ran their
large ranching operations. And thanks to
new technologies like the refrigerated
rail car which could transport beef long
distances without it spoiling, western
ranching was fully integrated into the
growing American economy. Okay, so
agriculture and ranching was falling
into the hands of big business types and
all those independent farmers whom
Thomas Jefferson was crying about were
getting pressed on all sides by these
big corporations. For example, railroad
companies were charging farmers
exorbitant prices to ship their products
on trains and for using storage
facilities like grain elevators. Then
further adding to their aggra misery,
prices per bushel of corn or wheat or
whatever steeply declined during this
period, further putting pressure on
small farmers who couldn't cut it by
selling their crops at such low prices.
And that happened precisely because
these big businesses could afford to
sell their products cheaply since they
operated at such a massive scale. And
all of this was compounded by the fact
that railroad companies were often given
land grants by the federal government in
order to build their lines. And whatever
land they didn't use, they were
authorized to sell to farmers. And those
railroad tycoons rarely passed up an
opportunity to inflate the price of that
land for their own profit, but to the
detriment of farmers. And so in
response, farmers across many states
began to organize to resist the
corporate takeover of their way of life.
And there are two organizations that
I'll mention. First, in 1868, farmers
banded together to create the national
graange movement, otherwise known by its
sassier name, the Graange. Now, it began
as a social and educational program for
farmers who, by the nature of their work
and geography, remain largely isolated
from one another.
>> Hey, can I borrow your rake?
>> What? However, a few years later, the
Graange shifted its focus to work for
the prosperity of individual farmers
against the interest of big business by
getting all political. For example,
Graange members lobbyed legislators in
several western states to provide
regulation over the prices railroads
charge to carry their crops to market.
And as you might imagine, the railroad
businesses resisted such a curtailment
in their profits. And so, they
challenged these laws in court. But
farmers scored a big victory in the
Supreme Court case called Munv. Illinois
in which the court ruled that such
regulatory oversight of railroad
corporations was indeed constitutional
because it was in the public interest to
keep food prices low. Anyway, the second
group I'll mention is the Colored
Farmers Alliance. Now, don't miss that
the periods for unit 5 and unit 6
overlap. And that means that all the
stuff that we're talking about right now
is going on during reconstruction with
all of its strain on race relations and
whatnot. Anyway, economic hardship fell
on Texas farmers in the 1880s due to the
combined forces of commercialization and
decreasing prices for their agricultural
goods. So Texas farmers also organized
themselves to fight against this
corporate takeover and to protect their
interest. However, since it was Texas
and it was right after reconstruction,
black farmers were very much not welcome
in the Texans farming cooperative. So,
black farmers went ahead and formed
their own cooperative and the colored
farmers alliance and it worked for many
of the same outcomes as the grains.
Okay. Now, everything I've been flopping
my mouth hole about was really just a
prelude to the main show, which is the
effects of westward migration during
this period, and there are three big
ones you need to know. So, the first
effect of westward migration was
economic growth. So, the
transcontinental railroads knit together
the entire territorial United States
into a giant interconnected economic
hugfest. And while there are so many
examples of the effects of that hugfest,
I'm only going to give you two. First,
the market for bison exploded. Now,
massive herds of bison once roame the
Great Plains region and served as a
chief source of food and raw materials
for American Indians who had lived
there. And the American Indians who
hunted the bison used every part of the
animal. They ate the meat. They
fashioned shelter from the hides. They
carved tools from the bones. I could go
on. But the flood of American migration
westward coincided with an increasing
demand for bison pelts in the eastern
markets which were made into hats and
other expensive kinds of clothing. And
as a result, American hunters nearly
drove the bison to extinction by over
hunting them. Additionally, the hunters
only took the pelts from the animals and
left the rest of the carcass to rotten
waste in the sun. But regardless, that
led to significant economic growth. And
then the second example of economic
growth was with respect to cattle
ranchers. You see, as Eastern Americans
began demanding more beef in their
diets, cattle ranchers in the west got
busy meeting that demand. For example,
as Texas re-entered the Union after the
Civil War, the Missouri Pacific Railroad
was completed, which linked all the
lands west of the Mississippi to eastern
markets. Therefore, cattle ranchers
drove their herd from Texas north to the
railroad terminus and sold them to
customers in distant eastern markets.
And for them, it was a massive payday
since the same steer that would sell for
a few dollars in Texas could sell for 10
times as much in the east. And so, like
I mentioned earlier, cattle ranching was
integrated into the national economy.
But then the second major effect of
westward migration was the creation of
boom towns which by definition refers to
a settlement that experiences rapid
growth because of a sudden economic
prosperity. And a good example of a boom
town is Virginia City, Nevada. So after
much of the surface level gold had been
mined in California prospecting
Americans looked around for a new place
to mine precious minerals and they found
it in 1859 with the comtock load in
Nevada. It was a massive deposit of
silver buried beneath the mountains and
it drew thousands of migrants almost
overnight. And as was the case in
California and other places where
precious minerals were discovered, the
sudden influx of migrants led to the
creation of a boom town called Virginia
City. And for about a decade, Virginia
City grew and prospered and they built
saloons and theaters and all the
trappings of a traditional town. But by
1870, the silver and the comtock load
had become unreachable by common miners
without industrial machinery and the
town was evacuated almost as quickly as
it was populated. And finally, the third
major effect of westward migration was
the establishment of new communities,
most notably immigrant communities. You
see, all the new economic opportunities
that arose during the California Gold
Rush and the building of the
transcontinental railroad attracted
large numbers of immigrants. And since
much of that opportunity was located on
the western coast, an overwhelming
amount of these immigrants came from
China. And so, Chinese workers played an
outsized role in the construction of the
railroads. But they were paid less than
white workers and eventually became the
target of a renewed anti-Chinese nivist
campaign, which resulted in the Chinese
Exclusion Act of 1882. Even so, many
Chinese immigrants banded together to
create their own communities, as they
did in the Chinatown districts of
Seattle and San Francisco. And as
Chinese people in the US were
increasingly barred from more and more
industries, they were forced to carve
out their own opportunities where they
could. And a significant example here is
the rise of Chinese laundry houses in
the second half of the 19th century in
places like San Francisco and New York
City. So, these were places where
Chinese immigrants washed clothes for
pay. And this kind of business had
several benefits for the Chinese. For
example, it required very little startup
money and it didn't require the
launderer to speak that much English.
Additionally, it was work that many
native-born Americans would not do for
themselves. And so, in that way, Chinese
immigrants, though their lives were made
exceedingly difficult by nivist
restrictions, were able to integrate
themselves into the growing American
economy. Okay, click here to watch my
other videos for unit 6, or you can
click here to check out my A pushheimler
review guide, which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible for
your exams. I'm glad you came by and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm lur
out.